Hi and welcome back to the channel. This time i'm
going to take fifteen minutes I have
and build
a really small blog engine.
I'm going to use
as a framework, the Perl Dancer framework
that you can see here:
perldancer.org
and i'm going to use obviously Padre
and the Padre on Strawberry
distribution
So I am going to use it on Windows.
So what we need is ... Let's start
Strawberry Perl ... Padre
We need an editor and when we open it
we are going to get an empty page.
Dancer comes with a command line application
that allowes us to build a skeleton of the application.
For this I need to
run
cmd and let's say change the directory to
the work directory
and here I am going to create the skeleton.
So I type in "dancer -a" and the
name of the application
which I picked Dwimmer
as the name
as some kind of ... magician or
whatever
so I'm going to call this a application
Dwimmer
is ..
Running this script will create
a subdirectory for
the application and then various files
that are the skeleton of the application.
If I go into this directory I can type
in perl bin
and the name
app.pl and run the application. This already
runs the skeleton
and I can switch to the browser and
type in localhost:3000
and it will bring up the default page
that Dancer created for me.
How does it look like?
So I go back to Padre and open the file
If I open the file
the file is .. if I recall it's in work
Dwimmer
and then there was the bin directory app.pl
So you can see that the script itself
is almost empty
it only loads the Dwimmer module
The Dwimmer module is in the lib directory.
In order to see it better
let's open the project browser
and Padre automatically recognizes the
project the
Perl project.
So it's in the lib directory there is the
Dwimmer.pm
and here is the applications so this
defines that there is a
when the user comes in with
a GET request
to the main page
then this subroutine should be
executed
which just loads the index template.
The templates are
located in the views subdirectory so
index.tt
is that template
What we...
Dancer comes with a really simple
template system
but I already installed
the Template::Toolkit
that comes with Padre on Strawberry Perl
so the first thing I
would like to do is to change the
template system.
That I can do in the config.yml file
that's in the root directory
of the application.
Here you'll see that there is the
template which is the simple template
and ... I would like to use the
Template::Toolkit
and even there
I define that the encoding is utf-8.
Now the start tags and the end tags I leave it as
the default in Dancer
which is
which looks
like this
so I leave it like that.
Now I configured that, I would like to see
that still working
so I
stopped the application, restarted
and go back to the browser
to see these still working.
What we saw earlier that there all kind of
values here
that are coming from
from the
template systems. So I reload it and I
still get the same thing
I still get the same data. Everything is OK.
Now
I don't need all that stuff that is in the default
view of Dancer
so I go into the index template
I delete everything and instead of that
I write hello
and
I tell the user to go to this page
to create a post
OK
So that's .. what I am going to
do
and ...
if we now reload the page
then that's what we have here: hello and
then a link to create a post.
Which should lead us to the page.
When I click on it I get a 404
error because no one
defined yet
what to do
if someone gets to this page.
and that's what the next thing we have
to do. So we go back to the module
and define
when someone get..
sends a GET request
to this page, then
call the subroutine
which is implementers here
and
load the template which is called
"page" in our case.
We have to still implement that template
so we go back to the index.tt
and
save it now
as "page.tt" and in there now I would
like to, instead of this..
and I would like to have a form.
The form
is going to
send in the request with
the POST method because we are posting
something and has an input field
which is
called
title. Right.
and then we also have another
input field
which is of type
submit
and in between
there is a text
area
textarea where we are going to type
in the text.
So this is the page.
Now if I go
and
reload the application
then, well oh, there is an error.
So semicolon seems to be missing that's
a standard error I make
here in the module, yes, this one.
So at the end we should never forget
the semicolon here
even though it looks like a subroutine
but it's actually a parameter to
the get function.
Now I can go and run it again and it
works better
... so I can go back to the page and
reload this and you get the form.
Which is a bit broken here
so let's try to make it a
bit nicer
I go back into the editor,
into the...
this template and first of all let's
make it a
little bit wider
and then put a break at the end and
make this textarea also
let's say have
10 rows, and let's have
80 columns
so it will be the same size
and then
also the submit button, instead
of "Submit Query"
let's say
put there a
value
which is Post
and then
if I reload now the page.
Then looks way better even though
the 80 here and the 80 here are
not the same. Strange,
I never understood that one.
Probably someone of you would like to explain it
to me
and then there's the post button.
Sort of looks ok as the first version.
So now if I type in some kind of a title,
and as some kind of ...
my text
then, ... well let's say something else
let's say hello, hello HELLO!
and I click on Post
then I get some strange...
it's getting not... not
it's sending in the title
but it does not send in the text..
let's see what did I do wrong
so...
I didn't give a name for it for example
so I need to give a name to this one.
Its called test
and it's meth..do, it's method
so I have to make ...
fix these issues
and then
I can come back, here
reloade the whole
page and then let's say hello
and this would be
world
and if I click on post then I get an error.
That's much better.
Now why did I get this error?
I get this error because this is a POST
request and not a GET request.
which is okay that's what I wanted
but I didn't write here what to do
when we
reach a
POST request.
So I a want to define it
and I say
if I get a POST request to this page
then call this other subroutine
which does something different.
So what does this .. ah .. don't forget
the semicolon.
So what does this do?
This needs to get the params
method and from there to fetch the
title value
and first thing let's say just return this one
so I
stop this
restart the application
and see again
If I reload the page and resend the
data then
I get back hello which is what the title
I wrote
so that's okay that works. We need to save it somewhere.
I could use some kind of
a database
but I want to make it the more simple
in this case. I am going to use a
JSON file.
So where is this JSON file?
We have to define it
in the configuration file.
In the configuration file I type
in dwimmer
which is the name of the application
and below this I'll save all the
data of the application
And then let's say
I call the field json and put there
the name of the file.
Where I am going to save all the data.
So this file is going to be my database.
and how do I get the data
I type in config
this function gets all the configuration data
and here I can type in the keys
and it has two keys. This is the name
of the file where the
data is going to be.
So I put it into a variable just so I have it,
make it simple
I put in a variable.
Then I need to read in the data from
that file. So I read
typing read_file and the name of file
and put this into a variable
but this data is going to be json.
Right? Because there, what we are saving
that is json. So I
put into a variable called $json
and then I still have to turn this data into
a Perl data structure
so
from_json is the function that
will take the json string
and return the data we need
so this is a data structure.
Now obviously the first time we run this we
won't have a json file there. In that case
we just want to have empty hash
to be returned
The way we can do this is we can check
wether there is..
the file, if it exists
and if it does then we call...
read in the file. if it doesn't
then we just
return a string with two curly braces
which is the way json defines
an empty hash.
So that's how we get an empty json
there
and then the data and now we just have to
add the new piece of ... the new
blog entry.
For this first of all we take the timestamp.
We have have new
variable called $now
and I put in a timestamp
and then
add to this data
"now" is going to be the key
so we are saving the pieces of
blog entries
according to the timestamp they have
and here I can add
title
and I just take it from here
because I don't need it there anymore
and I also have the text
from the user
and this is form the params text
and that's it.
Now
we have the data,
the new blog entry in the $data
and we just have to save it
which is using the write_file
giving the name of the file
and the
data. Now the $data is a
perl data structure I want to
save it as json so we have to
convert it to_json.
That's it.
Once it's done
we want to save this thing.
Sorry, we want to show
something to the user,
we want to redirect
redirect the user to the root,
to the main page.
On the main page we don't
yet show the content is
but let's see what, how does this work?
So for this to work I'll have to stop the
application again and start it again
and if I did not make any mistakes then it
might even work.
so, this is
the form. I filled it in and then I click post
and I get a runtime error. So this is the error.
Can't locate object method write_file.
Well, obviously
because
...
the from_json and the to_json functions
are part of Dancer
but the read_file and the write_file
are not.
So we have to load a module that will
provide them.
use
File
::
Slurp
is the name of the module and it
provides a read_file and a
write_file function.
So I save them. Now I have to restart the
application because I changed the code
and try this again so I go back
and
post it again
and here we are so
it sais its OK. It returned to the ..
the root web page, the main web page
but I don't see
any data yet so let's see first of all that the
data was saved.
I go back to Padre and I you go
back to the work directory. We said that
dwimmer.json is going to be there and
here we are. So there is the timestamp
at the text and the title we wanted
to save.
So it seems that it is saving into the
file. Now let's try to display it
on the
that page.
For this we go
to the
main page and here what we need
is to read in the data again.
Just the same way as we did it here. So the
simple thing is now just to copy-paste
this data.
and then we have all the data in this
variable called $data
and we would like to send it as
a parameter to the template.
so
we just send in
as a parameter to the template.
In the template
let's see what is in the template.
So this is the page
Here is the index template.
In the template
we would like to show
the data
which is actually .. now we .. that's a hash
So how do we fetch a hash
in the Template::Toolkit
and display to the user?
In Template::Toolkit is a
generic thing so you have a for loop
and then you put in a variable which is
let's say
page
and that does into and we have the data
rather than it is a cash so we have
to fetch the keys of it,
dictionary it is also called, and we would like
to make them sorted so
we sort them
That's the way to go over all the elements
of this hash
and then
we END it this way.
Inside now I can display
the actual content of this
variable called "p"
which is going to be the timestamp.
Now if i go back to the
I have to restart it because I just changed the
code as well, so
if I reload this page than we see
the timestamp of the only post we had.
Now that's nice but
we would like
to see the title and a content.
The way to do this in the Template::Toolkit
is to say that I would like to print
data
and then the p is now a variable so
I put a $ sign infront of it
and the "title" key of it.
And after that we would like to see text. Right?
So we would like to see all these.
If I go back to the web page and
reloaded and I don't need to restart the
application because I only changed the
template
and I see "hello world" which is the title and
the text. ..and.. let's meet
it a bit nicer
Let's put and H2
arround the title
and let's put
a horizontal row
infront of the ...
blog entry so here we are
there is this title part and then hello
the title of the post. Now let's
create another post
just to make sure that it's still working
so ... second post
more text
and I post
and here we are so we have now a first post
a second post
and we have a blog engine
thank you for watching ... if you want
to
posts on the Dwimmer
there is actually dwimmer.org or so you can
see it and you can go to perldancer.org and download
its cool, I like it.
thank you very much for watching
bye-bye